Okay שבוע טוב *Shavuah Tov* שנה טובה *Shanah Tova* everybody. Hope you
had a good ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. *Rosh Hashanah* meaningful ראש Rosh
השנה *Rosh Hashanah* and שבת תשובה *Shabbat Shuva*. We pick up today's
דף daf? *Daf* דף ע *Daf Ayin* 70. We pick up on
סט עמוד ב samech tes amud bais. *Samech-Tet Amud Bet*. We've begun
בן סורר ומורה ben sorer umoreh *Ben Sorer u-Moreh*. We finished up
the end of the last פרק *Perek* was a very fascinating אגדתא
*Aggadata* about the deathbed scene of רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* with the
whole subtext as I said shared at the time where we heard
from Wendy who shared a whole approach about seeing questions about the
pedagogy of רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* and I believe there was a
whole subtext going on there about the whole different approach to תורה
Torah שבעל פה *Torah she-ba'al peh* between רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* and
רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*. רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* very much about מסורה
*Mesora* רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* about sort of creativity and discovery and
so on. Anyway and now we turn to בן סורר ומורה ben
sorer umoreh, *Ben Sorer u-Moreh* where the major where we're dealing with
exactly the age that he has to be between 13 and two
pubic hairs, the משנה Mishna. *Mishna* says till he has a full
amount of pubic hair or not completely full but whatever and then
we had this statement in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* though that said
gave a time limit was a maximum of three months based on
some principle about בן *ben* and when it would be fit to
call somebody father like once he was had two pubic hairs he
could get somebody pregnant and then he would be seen to be
a father after three months so there's a three months upper limit.
And of course we introduced the idea that a בן סורר ומורה
ben sorer umoreh? *Ben Sorer u-Moreh* is נידון על שם Shem סופו
*nidon al shem sofo* that it's because of anticipating that in the
end he'll become addicted and he'll wind up robbing and even murdering
to feed his habit although I mentioned at the time and we'll
mention again the approach of רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* who emphasized that the
real point is וכל ישראל ישמעו ויראו *ve-kol yisrael yishme'u ve-yira'u* all
the people will be afraid and will fear and that says by
there and by זקן ממרא *zaken mamreh* and by הנביא נביא שקר
*ha-navi navi sheker* and by עדים זוממים *edim zomemim* and all those
people says רמב"ם *Rambam* could be argued are not being punished proportional
to their sin but to for the sake of protecting the institutions
of authority in society that of God of the בית דין *Beit
Din* of parents and so on. So that also seems a way
of certainly of understanding the sort of disproportionate aspect here. Anyway we're
in the middle of this point about how old somebody has to
be in order to sire children and
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says 13 and here it's though saying
that in the time of the תנ"ך *Tanakh* actually people were able
to do it boys were able to do it at the age
of eight and that there's a debate of בית הלל בית שמאי
*Beit Hillel Beit Shammai* whether to consider something an act of intercourse
להלכה lehalacha *le-halakha* at the age of eight since at the age
of eight in the time of תנ"ך *Tanakh* they were even able
to sire children. Now we're going to try to prove that this
is the case that they were able to have kids in the
time of תנ"ך *Tanakh* at the age of eight. The boys in
בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer u-Moreh *Ben Sorer u-Moreh* though? Correct. No
no this is a side point. Okay so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says like this ודרשו הראשונים *u-darsho ha-rishonim* first wide line on סט
עמוד ב *Samech-Tet Amud Bet* הראשונים מנלן דאוליד *ha-rishonim minalan de-olid* where
do you know that the earlier generations were able the boys were
able to get someone pregnant at the age of eight? אילימא מן
דכתיב dechativ *ileima min de-ktiv* הלא זאת בת
שבע Batsheva בת אליעם
אשת אוריה החתי *halo zot bat sheva bat eliam eshet uriah ha-chiti*
וכתיב vechtiv *u-ktiv* אליעם בן אחיתופל Achitophel הגילוני *eliam ben achitofel ha-giloni*
וכתיב u'vchtiv, *u-ktiv* וישלח ביד נתן הנביא ויקרא שמו ידידיה דשלמה בעבור
השם *vayishlach beyad natan ha-navi vayikra shemo yedidya de-shlomo ba'avur hashem* וכתיב
u'vchtiv, *u-ktiv* okay so what's about there about שלמה Shlomo *Shlomo* being
born hold on let me double check רש"י rashi *Rashi* here
oh and then the immediately next person verses right after שלמה Shlomo
*Shlomo* was born and שלמה Shlomo *Shlomo* remember is בת שבע Batsheva
*Bat Sheva*'s son actually second son the first one died וכתיב u'vchtiv,
*u-ktiv* ויהי לשנתים ימים *vayehi lishnatayim yamim* it was after two years
ויגזים לאבשלום *vayigozim le-avshalom* they were shearing the sheep for אבשלום Avshalom
*Avshalom* וכתיב *u-ktiv* ואבשלום ברח וילך גשור ויהי שם Shem שלש שנים
*ve-avshalom barach vayeilech geshur vayehi sham shalosh shanim* אבשלום Avshalom *Avshalom* ran
away and he was in גשור *Geshur* for three years so it's
now five years since the birth of שלמה Shlomo *Shlomo* וכתיב *u-ktiv*
וישב אבשלום Avshalom, בירושלים שנתים ימים *vayeishev avshalom bi-yerushalayim shnatayim yamim*
he was sitting there for two years now up to seven ופני
המלך לא ראה *u-fnei ha-melech lo ra'ah* ויהי מקץ ארבעים שנה ויאמר
שלמה Shlomo למלך אלכה נא ואשלם את נדרי אשר נדרתי להשם בחברון
*vayehi mi-ketz arbaim shana vayomer shlomo la-melech elcha na va'ashalem et nedari
asher nadarti la-hashem be-chevron* after 40 years so that was 40 years
from the time they asked for a king okay וכתיב *u-ktiv* אחיתופל
Achitophel ראה כי לא נעשתה עצתו ויחבש את החמור ויקם וילך אל
ביתו *achitofel ra'ah ki lo na'asta atzato vayachvosh et ha-chamor vayakam vayeilech
el beito*
and then at that time it says אחיתופל Achitophel. *Achitofel* saw that
his plot was not being fulfilled and he went home and then
anyway he died אל ביתו עירו ויצו אל ביתו ויחנק *el beito
iro vayeitzav el beito vayichanak* וכתיב *u-ktiv* okay אנשי דמים ומרמה לא
יחצו ימיהם *anshei damim u-mirma lo yechetzu yemeihem*
now people of blood and of deceit will not live to half
their ages and a standard age is considered to be 70 ותניא
כל שנותיו של דואג *ve-tanya kol shnotav shel doeg* thirty-four, 34. He
didn't get to half his age. ושל אחיתופל Achitophel. אינן אלא ela,
ל"ג thirty-three, 33. Okay, so אחיתופל Achitophel died at the age of
33. All of that was to say, which was after seven years
after אבשלום waited after שלמה Shlomo was born. Did you get all
that? So, right, if you were following the פסוקים, psukim, right, it
had שלמה Shlomo was born, it
had שלמה Shlomo
being born, okay, and then it had like it had like what
was it? There was two years for אבשלום and then three years
and then two years, all those פסוקים psukim about אבשלום, okay, and
then right at this stage after seven years is when אחיתופל Achitophel
dies. Okay, seven years after שלמה Shlomo was born. Alright, and שלמה
Shlomo is the son of בת שבע Batsheva
who is the daughter of... no, the daughter of... the granddaughter of
אחיתופל.
What was it say? What was it?
אליאם Eliam or whatever אליאם Eliam or and the son of... and
who was the son of אחיתופל. Okay, so, so here we... and
אחיתופל is now dying at 33. Okay, so he was dead 33...
he was dead at 33, seven years after שלמה Shlomo was born,
so when שלמה Shlomo was born how old was he? 26. He
was 26 when שלמה Shlomo was born, and when שלמה Shlomo was
born שלמה Shlomo was his great grandson and he was 26. Okay,
so that's gonna be the point here.
Okay.
So, alright. וכמה הוי הוא תלתן ותלת vechamah havei hu taltan vetalat
he was 33. דהוה שלמה dahavah Shlomo שלמה Shlomo. was seven years
old, so you subtract seven, he was 26. פשו עשרין ושית pashu
esrin veshit he was 26 when שלמה Shlomo was born. דל תרתי
שני לתלתא עיבורי dal tartei shenai letlata iburei now
for the time for אחיתופל's wife to get pregnant and then אליאם's
Eliam wife to get pregnant and then בת שבע Batsheva to get
pregnant and to have a kid is about...
well yeah we'll get to two kids in a minute. Okay, so
we're going to assume... well you don't have to be a nine
months pregnancy, it could be a seven month pregnancy, that would be
21 months, round it off you got 24 months. So there's two
years worth of pregnancies going on there. Okay. So אשתכח דכל חד
וחד בתמני אוליד ishtachach dechol chad vechad betamnei oulid
everybody must have been eight years old. Right? I mean what would
be the youngest? If you divide it minus two is 24, so
if he was eight and then אליאם Eliam was eight and then
בת שבע Batsheva was eight, so by the time that שלמה Shlomo
was born he was 16... here he was 24. Okay. So that
shows you that they give birth at the age of eight.
Are we assuming that all these are obviously consecutive? In other words...
Yes, of course. Yes. Okay anyway. דכל חד וחד בתמני אוליד dechol
chad vechad betamnei oulid ממאי mimai says the גמרא Gemara how do
you know? דילמא תרוייהו בתשעה אולידו dilma tarvaihu betisha olidu
maybe the two men of this chain here gave birth at nine...
sired kids at nine, which is what we're saying is you know
normally by the way we say that it's funny because we say
להלכה lehalachah. that a boy can't have kids till he's 13, but
an act of intercourse begins at the age of nine. But here
the גמרא Gemara. is at least more comfortable saying that if we
can get this up to nine, that's at least more consistent with
our contemporary הלכה halacha you know even though we might say the
age of having... of being able to have kids changed but at
least the age of intercourse would remain at nine. So maybe each
one of them was nine.
The men
here. ממאי דילמא תרוייהו בתשעה אולידו mimai dilma tarvaihu betisha olidu ובת
שבע אולידה בשית uvat sheva olida beshit like the men... whole question
here is when can the men have kids? So maybe the men
here were nine and בת שבע Bat Sheva? gave birth and she
was only six.
משום דאיתתא בריא mishum deitita barya the woman is more healthy, she
can give birth at a younger age. דידה לא dida lo no.
דהוה ולד מעיקרא dahavah valad meiikara
שלמה Shlomo wasn't even her first kid. So this would have really
pushed her age down to seven even if you kept the men
at eight. Right? Because she had to have two kids. Okay so
anyway so this isn't going to prove it. This isn't going to
prove the age of the men because we could have בת שבע
Bas Sheva being very young. Okay. אלא מהכא ela meihacha okay from
here. אלה תולדות תרח תרח הוליד את אברם את נחור ואת הרן
eleh toldot Terach Terach holid et Avram et Nachor ve'et Haran and
אברם... Avram... okay fine. So תרח Terach had those three kids. אברם
גדול מנחור שנה Avram gadol miNachor shana אברם Avram was older than
נחור Nachor by a year and ונחור גדול מהרן שנה veNachor gadol
miHaran shana נחור Nachor was older than הרן Haran by
a year.
So presumably that was the order of birth.
So אברם Avram was therefore two years older than הרן. Haran. נמצא
אברהם גדול שתי שנים מהרן nimtza Avraham gadol shtei shanim meHaran וכתיב
ויקח אברם ונחור להם נשים שם אשת אברם שרי ושם אשת נחור
מלכה בת הרן אבי מלכה ואבי יסכה vayikach Avram veNachor lahem nashim
shem eshet Avram Sarai veshem eshet Nachor Milkah bat Haran avi Milkah
va'avi Yiskah so הרן Haran was the father of יסכה Yiskah and
we're going to say יסכה Yiskah was שרה Sarah that אברם Avram
married his niece. ואמר רבי יצחק יסכה זו שרה ולמה נקרא שמה
יסכה ve'amar Rabbi Yitzchak Yiskah zu Sarah velamah nikrah shemah Yiskah why
was her name called יסכה? Yiskah? שסוכה ברוח הקודש. she-sochah b'Ruach ha-Kodesh.
She saw with the divine spirit. היינו דכתיב, hayinu d'chtiv, כל אשר
תאמר אליך שרה שמע בקלה, kol asher tomar elecha Sarah shema b'kolah,
just the תורה Torah reading we read on ראש השנה. דבר אחר,
davar acher, so you listen to שרה. Sarah. יסכה שכל סוכין ביופיה,
Yiscah she-kol sochin b'yofyah,
everybody looked at her beauty. וכתיב, okay, so fine. So אברהם Avraham
married his niece שרה Sarah and he was two years older than
his brother הרן, Haran, שרה's Sarah father. וכתיב ויפל אברהם על פניו
ויצחק ויאמר בלבו הלבן מאה שנה יולד ואם שרה הבת תשעים שנה
תלד. u'vchtiv vayipel Avraham al panav vayitzchak vayomer b'libo haleven me'ah shanah
yivaled v'im Sarah habat tishim shanah teled. So he was ten years
older than שרה. Sarah. כמה קשיש אברהם משרה עשר שנין, kamah kashish
Avraham mi-Sarah eser shanin, ten years. וקשיש מאבוה תרתין שנין, v'kashish me-avua
tartin shanin, he was two years older than שרה's Sarah father הרן.
Haran. משתכח כי אולידה הרן לשרה בתמני אולידה. mishtakach ki oladah Haran
l-Sarah b'tamni olidah.
So when הרן Haran gave birth to שרה, Sarah, he was eight.
Wait, why is that? Because he was eight, אברהם Avraham
was
100, and...
oh, right, right.
He was two years older than הרן, Haran, and therefore whenever... wait,
I don't get it. Oh, right. Right. שרה Sarah had to be
born, right, שרה Sarah had to be born when אברהם Avraham was
ten years old. So שרה Sarah had to be born when הרן
Haran was eight. Good. Okay. So that proves you that הרן Haran
was eight. ממאי? mimay? How do you know? דילמא אברהם זוטא דאחוה
הוה? dilma Avraham zuta d'achva hava? Maybe אברהם Avraham wasn't the oldest
of the brothers, maybe it wasn't listed in birth order, maybe he
was the younger of the brothers. ודרך חכמתן קחשיב להו. v'derech chochmatan
k'chashiv lehu.
And the list is not in birth order but it's in order
of like, you know, wisdom order or importance order. תדע דקחשיב להו
כדרך חכמתן. teda d'kachshiv lehu k'derech chochmatan. I can show you that
sometimes the verse lists an order of kids and it's not the
birth order but the order of importance or of wisdom. דכתיב ויהי
נח בן חמש מאות שנה ויולד נח את שם את חם ואת
יפת. d'chtiv vayihi Noach ben chamesh me'ot shanah vayoled Noach et Shem
et Cham v'et Yaphet. So based on this we think that שם
Shem would be the oldest son, את שם את חם ואת יפת.
et Shem et Cham v'et Yaphet. שם גדול מחם שנה וחם גדול
מיפת שנה. Shem gadol mi-Cham shanah v'Cham gadol mi-Yaphet shanah. נמצא שם
גדול מיפת שתי שנים. nimtza Shem gadol mi-Yaphet shteishanim. So according to
this שם Shem, is two years older than יפת. Yaphet. וכתיב ונח
בן שש מאות שנה והמבול היה מים על הארץ. u'vchtiv v'Noach ben
shesh me'ot shanah v'hamabul hayah mayim al ha'aretz. He was 600 years
old, right, and his first kid was when he was 500. Okay.
וכתיב, so that would mean that יפת Yaphet would be 98 at
most. וכתיב אלה תולדת שם שם בן מאה שנה ויולד את ארפכשד
שנתים אחר המבול. u'vchtiv eleh toldot Shem Shem ben me'ah shanah vayoled
et Arpachshad shnatayim achar hamabul.
שם Shem gave birth to ארפכשד Arpachshad two years after the מבול.
mabul. So and that he was 100 years old. But he should
have been 102 since he was 100 when the מבול mabul occurred
and it says he gave birth two years after the מבול, mabul,
so he should have been 102. בן מאה שנה? ben me'ah shanah?
What do you mean 100 years? בר מאה ושתים שנין הוה. bar
me'ah v'tartin shanin hava. He was 102. אלא דרך חכמתן קחשיב להו.
ela derech chochmatan k'chashiv lehu.
So it wasn't listing שם, Shem חם Cham and יפת Yaphet wasn't
the birth order. שם Shem actually was the third. He was 98
when the מבול mabul started, which is why he gave birth at
100 two years after the מבול. mabul. הכא נמי דרך חכמתן קחשיב.
hacha nami derech chochmatan k'chashiv. Here too it's the birth order. So
therefore שרה Sarah could have been,
you know, שרה Sarah could have been born when הרן Haran was
much older than merely eight years old.
ליהו. lehu. אמר רב כהנא אמריתה לשמעתא קמיה דרב זביד. amar Rav
Kahana amritah l'shma'ata kmei d'Rav Zvid. I said this from
of רב זביד Rav Zvid מנהרדעא. mi-Neharda'a. אמר לי אתון מהכא מותביתו.
amar li atun mehacha motvitu.
You trying to prove me from there? From אברהם Avraham or from
whatever, שלמה Shlomo and בת שבע? אנן מהכא מותבינן לה. anan mehacha
motvinan lah. We learn it out from here. ולשם ילד גם הוא
אבי כל בני עבר
אחי יפת
הגדול. u'l'Shem yulad gam hu avi kol bnei Ever achi Yaphet hagadol.
I'm sorry, excuse me. You learn out from there that the, excuse
me, that שם Shem was not the oldest son. We learn out
from here that שם was not the oldest son because it says
שם gave birth, the father of all the children of עבר, Ever,
the brother of יפת Yaphet the elder one. Okay. יפת הגדול שבאחיו
הוא הוה. Yaphet hagadol shebe-achav hu hava. יפת Yaphet was the oldest
one. So that's how we learn that that was not the birth
order. אלא מנלן? ela minalan? So what... isn't he himself אחי יפת?
achi Yaphet?
He is אחי יפת, achi Yaphet, but יפת Yaphet is הגדול. hagadol.
That's how it's reading it. And you could read it אחי יפת,
achi Yaphet, the brother of יפת, Yaphet, הגדול, hagadol, the oldest one.
But they're reading it אחי יפת הגדול. achi Yaphet hagadol. That's how
they're reading it. Okay, אלא, I understand. אלא מנלן? ela minalan? So
where do you know that they gave... that boys were able to
have children at eight? מהכא, mehacha, from here. It says ובצלאל בן
אורי בן חור למטה יהודה. u'vtzalel ben Uri ben Chur l-mateh Yehudah.
וכתיב, okay, that was the,
that was who it was, בצלאל Betzalel son of אורי Uri son
of חור. Chur. וכתיב
ותמת
עזובה, u'vchtiv vatamot Azuvah, who was the wife of כלב, Calev, ויקח
לו כלב את אפרת ותלד לו את חור. vayikach lo Calev et
Ephrat vateled lo et Chur. Okay, so חור Chur was now, we're
assuming it's the same חור, Chur, the son of כלב. Calev. ובהדי
דעבד בצלאל משכן בר כמה הוי? u'vhadi d-avad Betzalel mishkan bar kamah
havi? And how old must בצלאל Betzalel have been when he made
the משכן? mishkan? בר תליסר, bar tlisar, must have been 13. דכתיב
איש איש ממלאכתו אשר המה עושים, d'chtiv ish ish m'milachto asher hemah
osim, each man, so they were בר מצוה, bar mitzvah, 13. ותניא
שנה ראשונה עשה משה משכן שניה הקים משכן ושלח מרגלים. v'tanya shanah
rishonah asah Moshe mishkan shniyah hekim mishkan v'shalach meraglim.
So the first year he did the משכן, mishkan, so one year
out of Egypt they were doing the משכן. mishkan. וכתיב בן ארבעים
שנה אנכי בשלח משה עבד ה' אתי. u'vchtiv ben arbaim shanah anochi
bishloach Moshe eved Hashem oti.
And what's his name and כלב Calev says that he was 40
years when משה Moshe sent the מרגלים, meraglim, which meant that כלב
Calev was 30. eight when they well or thirty-nine let's say when
what do you call it during when they were building the משכן.
Mishkan. ועתה הנה אנכי היום בן חמש ושמנים שנה. Ve'ata hinei anochi
hayom ben chamesh ushmonim shana. Okay, כלב. Kalev. כמה הוו ליה ארבעין.
Kama havu lei arbain. So he was 40. דל ארביסר דהוה בבצלאל
Dal arbaisar dehavei beBetzalel so means he was 39 when they were
doing the משכן Mishkan because they sent the מרגלים meraglim in the
second year minus 13 that בצלאל Betzalel must have been 13 years
old, so he was now 26
when בצלאל Betzalel was born. Okay, פשלו עשרין ושית pashlu esrin veshis
26.
דל תרתי שני דתלתא עיבורי Dal tartei shnei detlasa iburei the year
of pregnancy, right? No, not the year of pregnancy.
He was he was בצלאל Betzalel was 13 when they were doing
the
משכן Mishkan and he was 40 at year 2 of יציאת מצרים.
Yetziat Mitzrayim. Yes, to year 2. Year 1 of יציאת מצרים Yetziat
Mitzrayim which is when they made the משכן, Mishkan, he was 39.
בצלאל Betzalel was 13. 39,
thank you, 39, בצלאל Betzalel was 13. So he was 26 when
בצלאל Betzalel was born. Okay, so 39 minus 13. Now it is
who now and the order is בצלאל בן אורי בן חור Betzalel
ben Uri ben Chur and חור Chur we are saying is the
who is חור Chur one minute yeah he was the son of
כלב. Kalev. Okay, so כלב Kalev was 26 when בצלאל Betzalel was
born.
Okay, so so that
meant
that he must have given had a kid at 8 and חור
Chur gave yes except that here you have all men. He gave
you know he gave he had a kid at 8, he had
a kid at 8, so that's 24 plus 2 years of pregnancy
by the three pregnancies so that allowed him to be 26 when
בצלאל Betzalel was born. Okay, so 39 minus 13. Now it is
who now and the order is בצלאל בן אורי בן חור Betzalel
ben Uri ben Chur and חור Chur we are saying is the
one minute yeah he was the son of כלב. Kalev. Okay, so
כלב Kalev was 26 when בצלאל Betzalel was born. Okay, so so
that meant that he must have given had a kid at 8
and חור Chur gave yes except that here you have all men.
He gave you know he gave he had a kid at 8,
he had a kid at 8, so that's 24 plus 2 years
of pregnancy by the three pregnancies so that allowed him to be
26 when בצלאל Betzalel was born.
Okay, so אשתכח דאוליד בתמניא אוליד. eshtakach deolid besamnya olyad. It's even
worse than that because the previous verse in דברי הימים Divrei Hayamim
says that כלב Kalev had already had children by an earlier wife.
Okay. All
right, so I guess I don't know what to say. Okay anyway
okay כמה הוו ליה דל ארביסר דהוה בבצלאל פשלו עשרין ושית
kama havu lei dal arbaisar dehavei beBetzalel
pashlu esrin veshis 26. דל תרתי שני דתלתא עיבורי אשתכח דאוליד בתמניא
אוליד. Dal tartei shnei detlasa iburei eshtakach deolid besamnya olyad.
So that's how we know in the earlier generations they gave birth
at 8 years old. Okay that was a very long proof for
that. Now an interesting side point about all of this is that
in the course of discussing all of this, right, it says that
they gave birth in the old generations at the age of 8.
But remember that it says if you think that it says the
age of בר מצוה Bar Mitzvah still was determined to be 13,
right, because it says בצלאל Betzalel was 13. And look at this
תוספות Tosafot of the previous דף ס״ט עמוד א׳. daf samech tes
amud alef. He says בידוע שאין לו גואלים. beyadua she'ein lo goalim.
This was the case of the kid who of the גר ger
who's a minor and you know that he doesn't have any redeemers
if he dies as a minor, right, because he couldn't have had
any kids. But here's the problem: if the age of בר מצוה
Bar Mitzvah would have always been 13, then when he died, okay,
he could have been like whatever 12 and a half because he
died as a minor. But at the time the תורה was being
written, they were able to have kids at the age of 8
according to what we just said. So why did it say you
know he didn't have any kids? Okay, so תוספות Tosafot says ואם
תאמר דמשמע דקתני בידוע שאין לו גואלים משום דאינו מוליד כדתנן אין
המולדת בין גדולה בין קטנה ופרש״י בת שמונה מאי קושיא המנו כמה
בשמעתין דדורות הראשונים היו מולידים בשמונה שנים. Ve'im tomar demashma dekasni beyadua
she'ein lo goalim mishum de'eino molid kedisnan ein hamoledes bein gedola bein
ktana uferash"i bas shmona mai kushya hamnu kama beshmaysin dedoros harishonim hayu
molidim bishmona shanim. Okay, ויש לומר ve'yesh lomar תוספות Tosafot says דאף
על פי שבדורות האחרונים נתנו חכמים שיעור בבת י״ב שנה ויום אחד
ובקטן בן י״ג שנה ויום אחד de'af al pi she'bedoros ha'achronim nasnu
chachamim shiur be'vas yud beis shana veyom echad uve'katan ben yud gimmel
shana veyom echad even though in later generations the age of majority
was 12 years or 13 years with two שערות sa'aros with two
pubic hairs, בדורות הראשונים שהיו ממהרים להביא
שערות bedoros harishonim shehayu memaharim lehavi sa'aros in early generations where presumably
they hit puberty at a younger age, the proof being that they
were able to have kids at a younger age based on what
we just said, היה זמן גדלות מקודם הרבה. haya zman gadlus mikodem
harbe.
So in the earlier generations the age of being an adult was
not 12 and 13. The age of being an adult was whatever
the normal age of puberty was. In those earlier generations, the age
of being an adult was like 8 years old for a boy
or whatever. So the actual הלכה halacha of what is defined as
an adult according to תוספות Tosafot changed with the changing of the
age of puberty based on the גמרא Gemara. that the original age
of puberty was 8 years old. והא דאמרינן לקמן דהוי בצלאל במשכן
בר י״ג שנה הוה דכתיב איש איש ממלאכתו. Veha de'amrinan lakamman dehavi
Betzalel bamishkan bar yud gimmel shana hava dikesiv ish ish mimlachto. So
why does the גמרא Gemara. say that בצלאל Betzalel had to have
been 13 since תוספות Tosafot is saying I just claimed now that
a person was considered a boy was considered a man at the
age of 8 in earlier generations? התם רוצה להוכיח על דורות ראשונים
ואפילו כהאי גוונא פרוש דהשתא לפי שלא פשט להוכיח Hasam rotze lehokiach
al doros rishonim va'afillu kehai gisa parush dehashta lefi shelo pashat lehokiach
whatever,
so תוספות Tosafot works it out. I don't want to get into
his answer but more fascinating I think, right, is you would tell
somebody right now, oh you know, you know the רבנים rabbanim determined
that the age of adulthood was 12 or 13 but I you
know earlier than that there was never that was not how the
age was defined at, you know, you'd be called a heretic. But
תוספות Tosafot right now says no, actually earlier than the period of
חז״ל Chazal when there was a younger age of puberty, they had
a different הלכתית halachic definition at what was considered to be an
adult. Yes, Joe.
In the 19th century in most of what we call the Right,
I understand that. That wasn't my interest, but okay.
Back to the גמרא. Gemara Okay, bottom of ס"ט עמוד ב'. בן
ולא בת. ben velo bas. תניא, Tanya, אמרו רבי שמעון, amru rebbi
shimon, בדין הוא שתהא בת סוררת ומורה כבן סורר ומורה. bedin hu
shetehei bas soreres umoreh keben sorer umoreh.
Really,
a daughter should be in the same category. Why? שהכל מצויין אצלה
בעבירה. shehakol metzuyin etzlah ba’aveirah. You know, if she basically goes wayward
and needs to feed a habit or something like that, she actually...
it's even more likely that she will, like, you know, be... have
a negative impact on the society, she'll lead people to sin, she'll
make herself sexually available, etc. So,
and presumably that's seen as bad as the concern that the boy
will turn to violent crime. אלא גזירת הכתוב היא בן ולא בת.
ella gezeiras hakasuv hi ben velo bas. Once again, this is a
גזירת הכתוב gezeiras hakasuv like other statements before in the גמרא. Gemara
Okay. משנה. מאימתי הוא חייב? me'imasi hu chayav? ע' עמוד א'. ayin
amud aleph.
What's today's official דף? מאימתי הוא חייב? משיאכל טרטימר בשר וישתה חצי
לוג יין. me'imasi hu chayav? misheyochal tartimar basar veyishteh chatzi log yayin.
What... what... I'm talking... when is he חייב? chayav? Because it says
זולל וסובא. zoleil vesovei. I mean, first he has to not listen
to his parents, and then they have to... they have to beat
him and then whatever, but anyway, but when they say here's what
he's doing, he's זולל וסובא, zoleil vesovei, he is basically a glutton
and a drunkard, okay? So that's defined as a certain amount of
meat and a certain amount of wine. A טרטימר, tartimar, what, Italian
wine? טרטימר, tartimar, which we'll see is basically a... a half a
מנה maneh of... excuse me, a half a מנה maneh of meat
and a half of a לוג log of wine, of... of Italian
wine. רבי יוסי אומר מנה בשר ולוג יין. rebbi yosi omer maneh
basar velog yayin. Double the amount. Okay. אכל בחבורת מצוה, achal bachavuras
mitzvah, if he ate it in the middle of doing some type
of, like, a מצוה mitzvah gathering, a nice wedding feast or something,
or אכל בעיבור החודש, achal be'ibur hachodesh,
as we'll see that they gathered to have a special feast when
they made a... when the month was a... was an עיבור ibur
month. Yeah, although it's interesting, yikes, maybe. But specifically this is עיבור
החודש, ibur hachodesh, not just ראש חודש. rosh chodesh. אכל מעשר שני
בירושלים, achal ma’aser sheni b’yerushalayim,
or they were eating מעשר שני ma’aser sheni in ירושלים, yerushalayim, so
it was a מצוה mitzvah eating. אכל נבילות וטריפות שקצים ורמשים, achal
nevelos utreifos shekatzim uremashim, or ate the opposite, things that were an
עבירה, aveirah, okay? You know, rodents and whatever,
and a טריפה treifah animal, animals that weren't שחט, shachted, somehow some
have the גירסא girsa here אכל טבל ומעשר ראשון שלא נטלה תרומתו
achal tevel uma’aser rishon shelo nutlah trumaso or טבל tevel that hasn't
taken its תרומה. trumah. You can't really say that because we're dealing
with meat here, so טבל tevel would not be a good example,
which is by... by produce from the ground, from the earth. ומעשר
שני שלא נפדה. uma’aser sheni shelo nifdah. Okay, so that's why those
are taken out because we're dealing with meat. But although that would
have been the normal thing to throw in normally when we're talking
about non-כשר kosher stuff. אכל דבר שהוא מצוה ודבר שהוא עבירה, achal
davar shehu mitzvah vedavar shehu aveirah, so that's the generic categories here.
אכל כל מאכל ולא אכל בשר שתה כל משקה ולא שתה יין.
achal kol ma’achal velo achal basar, shasah kol mashkeh velo shasah yayin.
If he ate every type of food, you know, under the planet
and completely made a glutton of himself but he never ate meat,
or he drank all types of beverages, all types of intoxicating things
but never drank wine, אינו נעשה בן סורר ומורה. eino na’aseh ben
sorer umoreh. You're not a בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer u-Moreh עד
שיאכל בשר וישתה יין. ad sheyochal basar veyishteh yayin. שנאמר זולל וסובא.
shene'emar zoleil vesovei. And although... so which is a glutton and a
drunkard. ואף על פי שאין ראיה לדבר, ve’af al pi she'ein ra’ayah
ladavar, now how do we know that means meat and wine? Well,
we can't prove it. זכר לדבר, zeicher ladavar, there's a hint that
that's what those words mean in the הלכה halachic context here, okay?
שנאמר, shene'emar, it says אל תהי בסובאי יין, al tehi besov’ei yayin,
do not be amongst the drunkards of wine, בזוללי בשר למו, bezolelei
basar lamo, or of the gluttons of meat. So even though that
verse is not about the הלכה halachic definition of בן סורר ומורה,
ben sorer u'moreh, it hints to the idea that that's what
our verse is referring to. Okay. And רש"י rashi says maybe that's
just an example of זולל וסובא, zoleil vesovei, it's not that זולל
וסובא zoleil vesovei is limited to wine and meat, but nevertheless that's
what we say להלכה.
And you eat it in one sitting?
Right. Let's take a look. Right, we'll get to that. Yes. אמר
רב זירא, amar rav zeira, right, it's not like over a period
of time. אמר רב זירא, amar rav zeira, טרטימר זה איני יודע
מהו. tartimar zeh eini yodea mahu. I don't know what the תנא
קמא tanna kamma here is... amount of a טרטימר tartimar is, okay?
אלא מתוך שכפלו רבי יוסי ביין, ella mitoch shekiflo rebbi yosi beyayin,
since רבי יוסי rebbi yosi doubled the amount of wine, the תנא
קמא tanna kamma said a half a לוג log and he said
a לוג, log, so נמצא כפלו אף בבשר, nimtza kiflo af babasar,
presumably he's doubling the amount of meat. And if he says it's
a מנה maneh of meat, נמצא טרטימר חצי מנה. nimtza tartimar chatzi
maneh. טרטימר tartimar is a half a מנה. maneh. That's good learning
from context. אמר רב חנא בר מולדא אמר רב הונא amar rav
chana bar molda amar rav huna (that was his father's name). אמר
רב הונא, amar rav huna, אינו חייב עד שיקח בשר בזול ויאכל
יין בזול וישתה. eino chayav ad sheyikach basar bezol veyochal yayin bezol
veyishteh. It's only if he... that he actually... he does not actually
steal the meat and wine. We're going to find out, well, how
do we even know he's stealing? It doesn't say he's stealing. But
we're going to say that he steals the money to pay for
it and he is stealing money and buying it when it is
cheap. Okay, that's going to be important. Okay.
Why? Because... but רש"י rashi says because if he's only buying very
expensive wine or meat, then we're not afraid that it'll become an
addiction because he won't be able to afford the addiction. Of course,
like you know, people get addicted to drugs which are very expensive
and they... and that's exactly what leads to them, but drugs are
a little more addictive than wine and meat. Okay, but רש"י rashi...
makes that key point here which we haven't said yet, that you
know, it's not just about being gluttonous, it's about getting an addictive
habit, which is why we're afraid about where it'll all lead. If
you look at רש"י...
Rashi And of course
people get addicted to drugs which are very expensive and that's exactly
what leads to them, but drugs are a little more addicting than
wine and meat. Okay, but there רש"י Rashi, makes a key point
there which we haven't said yet, that it's not just about being
gluttonous, it's about getting an addictive habit, which is why we're afraid
about where it'll all lead.
So look at רש"י, Rashi, יין בזול, yayin b'zol, יין בזול, yayin
b'zol, yes, it's going to be a pun word, but look at
רש"י, Rashi, יין בזול, yayin b'zol, he says אבל ביוקר לא שכיח
שכיח למות לגנוב כולי האי ולא ממשכי, aval b'yoker lo shchiach shchiach
leimot lignov kulei hai velo mamsheach, and the keyword is ממשכי. mamsheach.
Is he going to be drawn after this? Is this going to
become addictive behavior? Okay, so or you know, set him on a
path to perdition. So again as you said you can make the
argument just the opposite of this. Right, of course he's going to
need more money to do it.
Right, right. But again that works for things which are highly addictive.
Okay. אינו חייב עד שיאכל בשר בזול וישתה יין בזול eino chayav
ad sheyochal basar b'zol veyishte yayin b'zol and drink
it, דכתיב זולל וסובא dichtiv zolel v'sovei and yes it's a pun
word of
זול zol and
זולל. zolel. ואמר רבי חננאל בר מולדא אמר רב הונא אינו חייב
עד שיאכל בשר חי וישתה יין חי. v'amar Rabbi Chananel bar Molda
amar Rav Huna eino chayav ad sheyochal basar chai veyishte yayin chai.
It has to be like raw. Why? Because if it's basically well
let's take a look. איני eini is that really true?
והא רבה ורב יוסף דאמרי תרווייהו אכל בשר חי ושתה יין חי
אינו נעשה בן סורר ומורה. veha Rabba v'Rav Yosef d'amri tarveihu achal
basar chai v'shata yayin chai eino naaseh ben sorer umoreh. If it's
raw meat, יין חי yayin chai means it's not mixed wine, you're
not a בן סורר ומורה? Ben Sorer u'Moreh אמר רבינא יין חי
מזוג ולא מזוג, amar Ravina yayin chai mazug v'lo mazug, means it's
like a little diluted but not too much, so it's still very
powerful, that's the reason for the raw. Okay. בשר חי בשיל ולא
בשיל, basar chai bashil v'lo bashil, it's cooked but not fully cooked.
Exactly. כבשר כיבא דאכלי גנבי, k'vasar kiba d'achli ganvei, like meat on
a what do you call it on coals that thieves eat. Now
why is it important, what's this middle stage? So if you look
at רש"י, Rashi he says בשר חי, basar chai, רש"י Rashi says,
I'm sorry let's start with יין חי, yayin chai, ממשיך שמשובח הוא,
mamshiach shemeshubach hu,
so that draws you after it. והאי דמוקי ליה במזוג ולא מזוג
ובשר יין מזוג לא ממשיך. v'hai d'moki lei b'mazug v'lo mazug u'vasar
yayin mazug lo mamshiach. But if it's very diluted not, and presumably
if it's totally raw then maybe I don't know it's like it's
not tasty enough to be that type of a to develop that
addictive behavior so it has to be, you know, it can't be
100 percent, you know, it can't be 200 proof. Nobody can drink
200 proof. It has to be a high enough, a high enough,
you know, alcoholic content but still taste good in order to lead
you to become addicted to it. And
בשר חי, basar chai, כדמפרש לקמן בשיל ולא בשיל דדומיא דמדת גנב,
k'dimfaresh lekamman bashil v'lo bashil d'dumya d'middat ganav, that fits into the
whole life of living now a life of a גנב. ganav. You
know, you eat the meat and you're in a rush and so
on. אבל בשיל שפיר לא ממשיך. aval bashil shapir lo mamshiach. If
he's so, you know,
whatever, you know, refined that he only can eat fully cooked meat,
he'll never make it as a גנב. ganav. Okay. לא ממהר כגנבות
שמתחילה גונב ועושה בסתר אין לו שהות. lo mimaher k'ganvut shemit'chila gonev
v'oseh b'seter ein lo shehut.
So this predicts a life that he'll make it as a גנב
ganav but if it's totally raw then presumably also similarly that's not
tasty enough or good enough that we should be concerned about that.
Okay. Back to the גמרא. Gemara Okay.
אמר רבינא, amar Ravina, we just did it. אוקיי. okay. רבה
ורב יוסף דאמרי תרווייהו, Rabba v'Rav Yosef d'amri tarveihu, now רבה Rabba
and רב יוסף Rav Yosef both say אכל בשר מליח ושתה יין
מגיתו, achal basar maliach v'shata yayin migitto,
this is exactly the other extreme, salted meat which means it's not
cooked, it's just been salted to be preserved or whatever, and wine
that is now this isn't just not diluted but this is it's
right out of the pressing floor, it's not even it's like grape
juice essentially, right. אינו נעשה בן סורר ומורה. eino naaseh ben sorer
umoreh. Okay. תנן התם, tnan hatam, we taught over there. ערב תשעה
באב לא יאכל אדם שני תבשילין וכדי יאכל בשר ולא ישתה
יין. erev Tisha B'Av lo yochal adam shnei tavshilin u'chdai yochal basar
v'lo yishte yayin. Right don't eat meat and drink wine ערב תשעה
באב. erev Tisha B'Av. ותנא, v'tana, right they didn't have all practice
of the nine days there. אבל אוכל הוא בשר מליח ושותה יין
מגיתו. aval ochel hu basar maliach v'shoteh yayin migitto. But if it's
salted meat and it's or wine that's like freshly pressed that's not
a problem, that's not really like the pleasure of wine and of
wine and meat. Now בשר מליח עד
כמה, basar maliach ad kama, now how when is it considered בשר
מליח? basar maliach? ואמר רבי חנינא בר כהנא כל זמן שהוא כשלמים.
v'amar Rabbi Chanina bar Kahana kol zman shehu k'shlamim. As long as
it's like שלמים, shlamim, which רש"י Rashi means that it's been sitting
in the salt for two and for like two days and an
intervening night. That's the period you can eat שלמים. shlamim. Once it's
been sitting in salt that long in order to preserve it, it
loses its freshness and therefore it is no longer considered like really
good juicy meat and it's not a concern. ויין מגיתו עד כמה,
v'yayin migitto ad kama, until how long after it was pressed is
it still considered יין מגיתו? yayin migitto? כל זמן שהוא תוסס, kol
zman shehu toses, as long as it's still
bubbling. רש"י Rashi says like it's a little pungent when you drink
it. Okay. והתניא יין תוסס אין בו משום גילוי. v'hatanya yayin toses
ein bo mishum gilui. And now to what does that תוסס toses
period is, well we said that when the wine is still is
still bubbling or whatever it's not a problem of leaving it exposed
for fear that snakes will drink from it. וכמה תסיסתו, v'chama tsisato,
and what is that period? שלשה ימים, shlosha yamim, three days after
it's been pressed. Okay so basically meat after it's been salted for
two days and wine within the first three days of being pressed
is considered to be in this you know, so meat is in
the salted state after two days, wine is in the right out
of the pressing floor within the first three days.
Is this really like good wine?
What can I tell you. Anyway,
הכא מאי, hacha mai, so what's the שיעור shiur for ערב תשעה
באב? erev Tisha B'Av? Would it use the same שיעור? shiur? הכא
מאי. hacha mai. So the גמרא Gemara says התם משום שמחה הוא,
hatam mishum simcha hu, there the reason you don't do it on
ערב תשעה באב erev Tisha B'Av is that it brings joy. כל
זמן שהוא כשלמים נמי אית ביה שמחה. kol zman shehu k'shlamim nami
it bei simcha. And even after even as long as it's within
two days after being salted it might not be taste so fresh.
It's not super fresh, but it's still enough to be in give
you a nice געשמאק gishmak meal and it gives you שמחה. simcha.
Okay, כל זמן שהוא כשלמים נמי בשמחה. Kol zman shehu keshlamim nami
besimcha. הכא משום אימשוכי הוא hacha mishum imshuchei hu
but here it's not enough that it be a very gluttonous or
pleasurable meal. It has to be to the extent that it leads—and
here's the key word first in the גמרא—that Gemara. it draws you
after it. Okay, ובכל שהוא לא מימשך uvchol shehu lo mimshach and
maybe as soon as it's a little bit been salted and it's
not like really fresh, it's not going to like draw you after
that life, it's not so seductive at that stage or addictive. Okay,
so maybe even a, an hour after it's been salted. That's one
issue. ובכל שהוא לא מימשך. Uvchol shehu lo mimshach. ויין עד ארבעים
יום. Veyayin ad arbaim yom.
And maybe the wine is—is 40 days because it's after it's three
days, even so it's—even though it might not be a problem for
תשעה באב Tisha B'Av for שמחה, simcha, whatever, it could be again
that the wine is—does not create that addictive practice until it's really
begun to ferment, and less than 40 days would not be a
problem. So that's—so the גמרא Gemara sort of seems to be the
גמרא's resolution, like it says, it asks, and what's the story here,
and it seems to be saying—it suggests that this would be it,
but it seems to be also saying that this would be the
שיעור, shiur, would be a different שיעור. shiur. Okay. Now that we've
said that, we get—use this as an opportunity because we're now mentioning
the problem about the seductive
quality—qualities, or addictive qualities of wine, or of whatever, of being drawn
after your food, gluttonous behavior. So now we're going to both have
like a criticism
of indulgence in wine, but also a discussion about moderation it's not
so bad. So it's going to be an interesting גמרא. Okay. אמר
רבי חנן, Amar Rabbi Chanan, לא נברא יין בעולם אלא לנחם אבלים
ולשלם שכר לרשעים. lo nivra yayin ba'olam ela lenachem avelim uleshalem s'char
lereshaim.
So it's a very nice, pungent-like,
a kind of a statement, like what?
שכר. S'char. Yes, not שכר, shechar, שכר. s'char. Yes, but—okay, well I'll
tell you. Okay, so on the one hand wine does something good.
If somebody is really feeling down and depressed or whatever, a little
bit of wine can—can be good for them. Okay, but the—also for
people that are going to like pursue it and be and
become just get drunk all the time, that's going to be their
way of getting paid back in this world. So what does that
mean? So רש"י Rashi says, if you look at רש"י—where Rashi? is
רש"י?—רש"י says, ולשלם שכר לרשעים uleshalem s'char lereshaim שמתעדנים בו בעולם הזה
ומקבלים בו שכר מצוה שעשו בעולם הזה. shemitaadnim bo baolam hazeh umekablim
bo s'char mitzvah sheasu baolam hazeh.
So רש"י Rashi says actually no, not yet. It's not—because you could
have said שכר לרשעים s'char lereshaim is meant ironically. The רשעים reshaim
will follow wine and get drunk all the time and then that'll
be their comeuppance or whatever. But no, but רש"י Rashi is reading
this that—no, actually it brings pleasure, wine—wine brings pleasure to this world.
What do we need the pleasure—what do we need it for? We
need it for people
that are depressed and whatever and mourning and so on that it's
helpful for them, and for other people let them get the pleasure
and let them use up all their שכר s'char for עולם הבא.
Olam Ha-ba. Okay. שנאמר sheneemar תנו שכר לאובד ויין למרי נפש. tnu
shechar leoved veyayin lemarei nafesh. Give שכר shechar to the one who
is going to be destroyed, which is the רשעים, reshaim, and wine
to those bitter of soul. אמר רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak, which
is the mourners. אמר רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak, מאי דכתיב, mai
d'ichtiv, what's meant, אל תרא יין כי יתאדם? al tere yayin ki
yitadam? Do not look at wine just because it is ruddy. אל
תרא יין שמאדים פניהם של רשעים בעולם הזה. Al tere yayin shemaadim
pneihem shel reshaim baolam hazeh. Don't be seduced by wine that even
though it brings like ruddiness to the face of the רשעים reshaim
in this world,
ומלבין פניהם לעולם הבא. umalbin pneihem leolam haba. It'll cause them to
be like shamed in the world to come because of—because they'll have
gotten all their reward in this world. So some were saying, wine
is good, but like, in limited in specific contexts, either to pay
you up for your—for your שכר s'char and then you'll use up
all your עולם הבא, Olam Ha-ba, or for people that are in
particularly whatever, mourners and
so on. Yes.
Did the רמב"ם use this to say that this בן סורר ומורה
Ben Sorer u'Moreh has to drink red wine?
No, no, no. רבא אמר, Rava amar, אל תרא יין כי יתאדם,
al tere yayin ki yitadam, אל תרא יין שאחריתו דם. al tere
yayin sheacharito dam. Don't run after wine that in the end it'll
be blood. It'll cause your life, you'll become a בן סורר ומורה
Ben Sorer u'Moreh. or something like that, or you'll cause spilling of
blood. Okay, or whatever, just use up your שכר s'char in עולם
הבא. Olam Ha-ba. רב כהנא רמי, Rav Kahana rami, כתיב ktiv תירוש
tirosh וקרינן vekarinan תירש tirash without the vav וקרינן ביה vekarinan bei
תירוש. tirosh. Right, that's the wine, that's the Torah's word for wine.
זכה נעשה ראש. Zacha naaseh rosh. If you use it
responsibly—please drink
responsibly—then you become a head. It's helpful. לא זכה נעשה רש. Lo
zacha naaseh rash. If you don't—if you're not—don't merit, you don't drink
it responsibly, then you become poor, it impoverishes you.
רבא רמי, Rava rami, כתיב ktiv ישמח yismach וקרינן vekarinan
ישמא. yishma. I think is how it's going to read it, right?
ישמא. Yishma. We'll take a look. זכה משמחו, Zacha mesamcho, יין ישמח
לבב אנוש. yayin yismach levav enosh. If you merit it makes you
joyous. לא זכה משממהו. Lo zacha meshammehu.
It's like—I guess they're reading
ישמא. yishma. Yeah, exactly. From שממה. shmama. Right, I don't know how
they're reading
ישמח. yismach. What? ישמא. yishma. Anyway, it makes you, it makes you
desolate. והיינו דאמר רבא. v'haynu d'amar Rava. This is what רבא Rava
said. חמרא וריחני chamra v'reychani wine and like fragrances, פקחין pichrin have
made me have made me smart, you know they've been very helpful
for me, like so use these things in moderation. Who knows? Maybe
his maybe his ריחני reychani is like maybe he smoked a little
too or something. You know anyway, so you know used anyway, he
says used responsibly, it's all very good. אמר רב אמר בריה דרב
שמעון בר
אבא אמר רבי חנינא, Amar Rav Ammar brei d'Rav Shimon bar Abba
amar Rabbi Chanina, מאי דכתיב mai d'chtiv what's meant, למי אוי למי
אבוי l'mi oy l'mi avoy to who is woe to who is
moaning, למי מדנים למי שיח l'mi m'danim l'mi siyach who is fights
who has speech, למי פצעים חנם l'mi p'tzaim chinam who gets beaten
up for nothing, למי חכלילות עינים l'mi chachlilut eynayim who has ruddiness
of the eyes, למאחרינה על היין l'ma'achrina al hayayin those who stay
late drinking wine, לבאים לחקור ממסך l'vaim lachkor mimeisach those that come
to seek out we'll see what that means in a minute from
the from from libations. Okay, כי אתא רב דימי אמרי, ki ata
Rav Dimi amri, אמרי במערבא amrin b'ma'arava they say in ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael. Here's how to read the פסוק. pasuk. האי קרא מן
דדרש ליה מרישא לסיפא מדרש ומסיפא לרישא מדרש. Hai kra man d'darish
lei meireisha l'seifa midrash u'm'seifa l'reisha midrash. You can read it forwards
or backwards. What does that mean?
It means one way is reading it forwards is, you know, who
gets all of this woe? The people that obviously are staying and
drinking wine and they get into fights and they get beaten up
etc. That's read, and that's reading it forwards, forwards. What's reading it
backwards to forwards? One minute, let me see what רש"י Rashi says.
מדרש מסיפא לרישא מדרש שיהפך היאמר לו, Midrash min seifa l'reisha midrash
sheyehafek hayomar lo, מי שירשיע. mi sheyerasha. Oh,
it's the reverse. Who should, you know, who like like not that
the all the people, ah, the way backwards is, like if you
start at the end, because you have been, you know, are spending
all this time drinking wine and whatever, that leads to you having
woe and getting into fights etc. The other way to read it
is for the person who has woe, like the mourner and the
person who's been beaten up and so on, they could use a
nice drink to help them deal with their sorrow. So it's not
a criticism, it's saying, oh, if you've been just had a really
tough day, you know, a drink might help.
Yeah, especially if you drink a little bit, you come to the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
That is true. But here they're saying it's so good.
What? I mean here they're saying it's a good thing though.
It's a good, it's a good thing under certain circumstances, you know.
And that's the whole point, the whole point is to speak about
this and under certain contexts it's helpful, you know. It's not, we're
not it's not this what's it called, teetotaling or whatever, you know,
you know what was it, prohibition, right, you know, it's all evil.
No, you know, used responsibly it's a good thing and there's people
that, you know, it's helpful whatever.
But also המשלוח יין hamishloach yayin was a ברכה. bracha.
Right exactly, you know, it's just used irresponsibly.
Even the prohibition on mourners getting, you know,
drinking, they actually originally had ברכת ניחום אבלים birchas nichum aveilim
that they did with with glasses of wine and I think that
they had like thirteen glasses of wine or whatever and then they
realized that it was a little bit too excessive so they cut
back on it. But yes, it's true, you know, the what do
you call it, an אונן, onen, an אונן onen can't have wine
and but a mourner can, and one of the reasons specifically given
is although you can say wine is משמח, mesameach, but specifically given
is because it was understood to be helpful for them to deal
with their grief to have a little bit of wine. So, okay,
so the גמרא says like this. Okay,
עובר גלילא, over glila,
י"ג ווי"ן נאמרו
ביין, yud gimmel vavim ne'emru b'yayin, דרש עובר גלילא, darish over glila,
so this person עובר גלילא, over glila, the Galilean, made a דרשה.
drasha. י"ג ווי"ן נאמרו ביין, yud gimmel vavim ne'emru b'yayin, if you
say there is you know there's sixteen vav, there's thirteen vavs and
all the vavs are like saying are like woe, you know, are
sort of ויי ויי vai vai רש"י Rashi says, woe woe for
wine. Where are the thirteen vavs? ויחל נח איש האדמה vayachel noach
ish hadama that's one. ויטע כרם vayita karem he planted a vineyard.
וישת מן היין vayesht min hayayin three. וישכר vayishkar he got drunk.
ויתגל בתוך אהלו vayitgal b'toch ohalo he revealed himself, five. וירא חם
vayar cham six, אבי כנען את ערות אביו, avi ch'naan et ervat
aviv, ויגד לשני אחיו בחוץ vayaged lishnei echav bachutz seven. ויקח שם
ויפת את השמלה, vayikach shem vayefet et hasimla, so ויקח vayikach is
eight, יפת yefet is nine, although רש"י Rashi says תוספות Tosafos says
you don't count יפת yefet because that's just you have to it's
not linking the verbs you just have to say שם ויפת shem
vayefet so we're up to eight, את השמלה, et hasimla, וישימו על
שכם שניהם vayasimu al shechem shneihem nine. וילכו אחורנית vayelchu achoranis ten.
ויכסו את ערות אביהם vayechasu et ervat avihem eleven. ופניהם אחורנית u'pneihem
achoranis twelve. ויקץ נח מיינו vayikatz noach miyeino thirteen. Thirteen like things,
one led to the other led to the other led to the
other, like it's a powerful point, like you know you start drinking
especially thinking about the בן סורר ומורה, Ben Sorer u'Moreh. you know,
and then you you know one thing leads to the other and
you can't escape sort of the pattern, you know, that sort of
evolves from this get from from following after the wine. Okay. וידע
את אשר עשה לו בנו הקטן. v'yeda et asher asa lo b'no
hakatan. רב ושמואל חד אמר סרסו, Rav u'Shmuel chad amar sirs-, now
that we're talking about what happened that נח Noach allowed himself to
get drunk and the downfall of נח, Noach, right, this is the
object lesson about being, you know, about not being about being irresponsible
with wine. So what happened to him? So one said that what
his younger son did to him. What does his younger son So
one say he castrated him so that he shouldn't have any more
kids וחד אמר רבעו. v'chad amar riv'o. He had sexual intercourse with
him. מאן דאמר סרסו. man d'amar sarsno. So one say he castrated
him so that he shouldn't have any more kids וחד אמר רבעו.
v'chad amar riv'o. He had sexual intercourse with him. מאן דאמר סרסו.
man d'amar sarsno. מתוך שקלקלו ברביעי קללו ברביעי. mitoch she-kilkulo barvi'i killelo
barvi'i. So that works because he said he cursed Cham's fourth son
Canaan ארור כנען. Arur Canaan. Why did he curse Cham's fourth son?
Because Cham prevented him from having a fourth son. ומאן דאמר רבעו
uman d'amar riv'o that he had sexual intercourse with him סבר וירא
וירא. savar vayara vayara. And he saw what his son did דכתיב
הכא וירא חם אבי כנען את ערות אביו dich'tiv hacha vayara Cham
avi Canaan et ervat aviv that Cham saw his father's nakedness וכתיב
התם וירא אותה שכם בן חמור uch'tiv hatam vayara otah Shechem ben
Chamor by Dinah. So the same way there he raped her here
too he raped his father. בשלמא למאן דאמר סרסו bishlama l'man d'amar
sarsno if you say that he castrated him משום הכי קללו ברביעי.
mishum hachi killelo barvi'i. Now we get why he cursed his fourth
son. אלא למאן דאמר רבעו ela l'man d'amar riv'o that he raped
him מאי שנא רביעי mai shena revi'i נלטייה לדידיה? niltaye ledidei? Why
does he curse his fourth son? Why didn't he just curse Cham
directly? So the Gemara says חדה כהא וחדה כהא. chada k'ha v'chada
k'ha. Okay according to this version both were true. He both raped
him and he castrated him. So the castrating was why he cursed
his fourth son. Okay ויחל נח איש האדמה ויטע כרם. vayakhel Noach
ish ha'adamah vayita karem. He began and he planted a vineyard. אמר
רב חסדא אמר רב עוקבא ואמרי לה מר עוקבא אמר רב זכאי
amar Rav Chisda amar Rav Ukva v'amrei lah Mar Ukva amar Rav
Zakai אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא לנח. amar HaKadosh Baruch Hu l'Noach. God
says to Noach נח לא היה לך ללמוד מאדם הראשון? Noach lo
hayah l'cha lilmod me'Adam HaRishon? First thing you do right we're starting
a world anew. The comparison to Adam HaRishon is of course very
powerful. The world was תהו ובהו tohu vavohu then the earth shows
and then human beings come out onto the earth. You should have
learned didn't you learn your lesson from Adam HaRishon שלא גרם לו
אלא יין? shelo garam lo ela yayin? The עץ הדעת etz hada'at
according to this was the wine. That's what led
people astray. That was the first sin was the sin with wine.
You should have learned that that would not be the thing you're
supposed to start with.
Not only did people have children at a younger age but wine
takes minutes to ferment.
There you go. כמאן דאמר. k'man d'amar. Well I guess if they
could give birth right away. כמאן דאמר. k'man d'amar. I mean they
also gave birth Kayin and Hevel. כמאן דאמר אותו אילן שאכל ממנו
אדם הראשון גפן היה. k'man d'amar oto ilan she-achal mimeno Adam HaRishon
gefen hayah. This drasha assumes that that tree was wine of the
vine. Anyway דתניא d'tanya רבי מאיר אומר אותו אילן שאכל אדם הראשון
ממנו גפן היה. Rabbi Meir omer oto ilan she-achal Adam HaRishon mimeno
gefen hayah. It
was wine. What's that based on? So fits in with our whole
here discussion of about wine. שאין לך דבר שמביא יללה לאדם אלא
יין. she-ein lecha davar she-meivi yelala l'adam ela yayin. The thing that
brings woe to somebody is wine. You know you drink wine you
drink a little but it often leads to drinking too much and
then it leads to you getting addicted doing things you shouldn't have
done etc. etc. like we see by Noach. רבי יהודה אומר. Rabbi
Yehuda omer. So anyway that is the that was the tree that
was the eating that sort of leads people away from a life
serving God. רבי יהודה אומר חטה היה. Rabbi Yehuda omer chita hayah.
It was wheat שאין העץ נקרא עץ. she-ein ha'etz nikra etz. Okay.
שאין התינוק יודע לקרוא אבא ואמא
עד
שיטעום טעם דגן. she-ein hatinok yode'a likro aba v'ima ad she-yitom ta'am
dagan. Kids only are able to speak after they've eaten some solid
food eaten some wheat-based product. I don't know if that's true. They
start eating solids. When do they start eating solids?
Okay anyway and because so he's focusing on that it's an עץ
הדעת טוב ורע. etz hada'at tov v'ra. It's an עץ etz of
knowledge. So the association here with that the wheat gives a certain
intellect it's not just a coincidence of timing. The eating of the
kid when they start to eat wheat that helps their brain develop.
So the wheat is דעת טוב ורע da'at tov v'ra gives intellect.
It also looks beautiful lush thing. You know you look at a
stalk of wheat say I want to eat that.
Where does it say it was? וכי טוב העץ למאכל וכי תאוה
הוא לעינים. v'chi tov ha'etz l'machal v'chi ta'avah hu l'einayim. What can
I tell you? Okay.
Exactly. רבי נחמיה אומר. Rabbi Nechemya omer. Rabbi Nechemya said תאנה היה.
te'eina hayah. It was no it was a fig tree שבדובר שקלקלו
בו נתקנו. shebadavar she-kilkelu vo nitkanu. The thing that they sinned in
that was the thing they were they were able to hide themselves
among the fig leaves שנאמר ויתפרו עלה תאנה. she-ne'emar vayitperu aleh te'eina.
Now Rashi says that this is sort of like a reverse מידה
כנגד מידה. mida k'neged mida. If you look at Rashi בדבר שנתקלקלו
בו נתקנו. bidavar she-nitkalkelu vo nitkanu. Rashi says מידתו של הקדוש ברוך
הוא באיזמל שהוא מכה בו הוא מרפא. midato shel HaKadosh Baruch Hu
be'izmel she-hu makeh vo hu merape. With the same like awl that
God punctures somebody He uses it to heal the person. נס בתוך
נס. nes betoch nes. So God actually so it's sort of like
God this tree caused their downfall God wanted it to also be
the thing that at least came to protect them.
Like homeopathy. Oh
interesting.
Oh interesting. Okay כמו. k'mo. Alright. ויצת אש בציון וכתיב ואני אהיה
לה נאם ה' חומת אש סביב. vayatzet esh b'Tzion uch'tiv va'ani eheyeh
lah neum Hashem chomat esh saviv.
So the same thing that I punish her which is interesting because
Rashi sort of assigns the act of being punished to God like
not that they did the sin like God punished them through the
tree and now God healed them through the tree. תוספות Tosafot does
not like that. תוספות Tosafot says שאין ענין זה לזה כלל. she-ein
inyan zeh la-zeh klal. So תוספות Tosafot says the real story is
that after they sinned they wanted to go hide in the
trees but all the trees refused to accept them. Don't come to
us, we don't want any type anything to do with your sin.
And the only tree that was willing to to accept them was
the tree that actually was involved in their sin in the first
place. Okay, if you look at תוספות Tosfos about eight lines before
the
end, דהיו מחזרים על כל האילנות ולא היו מקבלין אותו. d'havu mechazrin
al kol ha'ilanos velo hayu mekabelin oso. מה היו אומרים לו? mah
hayu omrim lo? אמר ברוך זה הגנב דגנב דעתיה דבראיה amar baruch
zeh haganav deganav daateih d'vareia of this person who who דבראיה d'vareia
tried to like trick God. היינו דכתיב אל תבואני רגל גאוה hainu
dechtiv al tvo'eni regel ga'ava רגל שנתגאה בוראו regel shenisga'eh bora'o ויד
רשעים אל תנידני veyad resha'im al tenideni לא תצא ממני lo setzei
mimeni לא תסיב ממני lo tasiv mimeni עלי. alai. אבל התאנה על
ידי שאכלה ממנו פתחה לו דלתיה וקיבלה אותו. aval hate'enah al yedei
she'achlah mimeno pascha lo delaseiha vekiblah oso. So the tree was the
only one that had a little רחמנות rachmanus on it because it
it ate from that tree so it was prepared to accept them.
Anyway, דלתיה delaseiha I think it's door or whatever.
I don't know. שאכלה ממנו she'achlah mimeno like it opened up its
door to it. Okay.
Okay, where were we? Okay, now. So continuing with this theme of
wine, we're going to look at a section of משלי Mishlei
that that is a sort of a מוסר mussar about wine. So
let's take a look. It starts the following way: דברי למואל מלך.
divrei Lemuel melech. Okay, the words of Lemuel the king. משא אשר
יסרתו אמו. masa asher yisartu imo. The
משא masa is often used in משלי Mishlei like as like a
moral teaching, okay, but anyway, but the רש"י Rashi says right, פרשת
תוכחה parashat tochecha that his mother remonstrated him on. אמר רב יוחנן
משום רבי שמעון בן יוחאי למה איתה. amar Rav Yochanan mishum Rabi
Shimon bar Yochai lama aisa. So we're going to read this as
about שמואל... Shmuel... excuse me, שלמה. שלמה is talking about himself. מלמד
שכפתו אמו על העמוד. melamed shekafato imo al ha'amud. His mother tied
him to a post. ואמרה לו ve'amrah lo and said now this
is the continuation of the פסוק. pasuk. מה ברי ומה בר בטני
ומה בר נדרי. mah beri u'mah bar bitni u'mah bar nedari. Okay,
so what does that mean? מה ברי mah beri what is it
my son? הכל יודעין שאביך ירא שמים הוה. hakol yodin she'avicha yere
shamayim havah. Everybody apparently the story is that according to this שלמה
at a young age like what's the Shakespeare story about Hal or
whatever King Richard where he was like all he was like a
drunkard or whatever before he assumed the kingship? No, one of Shakespeare's
plays opens that way. Richard III? Richard III, right and he's out
he's there there carousing and drinking. Anyway, so according to this שלמה
was a was a little bit too much going after the wine
when he was still young at a very young age and his
mother beat him into shape to make sure that he did not
follow this path when he would become a king. בת שבע who
was six years old when she was
born. Okay. So. So. הכל יודעין מה ברי hakol yodin mah beri
you're my son. So people say it's my fault that you're my
son. הכל יודעין שאביך ירא שמים הוה. hakol yodin she'avicha yere shamayim
havah. Everybody knows that your father דוד Dovid is is God-fearing. עכשיו
יאמרו אמו גרמה לו. achshav yomru imo garmah lo. Now they're going
to blame me. ומה בר בטני u'mah bar bitni my son the
son of my belly. כל הנשים של בית אביך כיון שמתעברות שוב
אינן רואות פני המלך. kol hanashim shel beis avicha kivan shemisabrot shuv
einan ro'os pnei hamelech. All the your father's other wives once they
get pregnant they're not allowed into the king's king. ואני דחקתי ונכנסתי
ve'ani dechakti venichnasti I forced myself in in order to have sexual
relations with him even when I was pregnant כדי שיהא לי בן
מזורז ומלובן kedei sheyeheh li ben mezuraz umeluban because the belief is
that the sexual relations when you're pregnant makes the son turn out
better like a זריז ומזורז zariz u'mezuraz what? Vigorous. Thank you. ומה
בר... u'mah bar... so anyway but they'll say it's all my fault.
I made you so vigorous you're running after wine. ומה בר נדרי
u'mah bar nedari כל הנשים של בית אביך היו נודרות יהיה לי
בן הגון למלכות. kol hanashim shel beis avicha hayu nodros yehei li
ben hagun lemalchus. All the other king's wives were would make a
נדר neder that they would want their child to be fit for
kingship. ואני נדרתי ואמרתי יהיה לי בן זריז וממולא בתורה והגון לנביאות.
ve'ani nadarti ve'amarti yehei li ben zariz umimulei batorah vehagun lenivius. I
wanted you to serve to to get to religious heights heights and
now you're going to lead a life of following wine? אל למלכים
למואל. al lamelachim Lemuel. Not to the kings Lemuel. אל למלכים שתו
יין. al lamelachim sheso yayin. Not with the kings drink wine. אל
למלכים al lamelachim not to the kings. אמרה לו amrah lo מה
לך אצל מלכים mah lecha eitzel melachim why what are you why
are you spending your time with all those kings and whatever probably
princes ששותים יין ומשתכרים ואומרים למה לנו אל sheshosim yayin umishtakrim ve'omrim
lama lanu El they spend their time just drinking getting drunk and
they say למה לנו אל lama lanu El so that's the למואל.
Lemuel. What do we need God for? We have wine and a
good time. Okay. ורוזנים אי
שכר. veroznim ei shechar. מי שכל רזי עולם גלוים לו mi shekol
razei olam gluyim lo God who all of the secrets of the
world are revealed to him ישתה יין וישתכר. yishteh yayin veyishtaker I'm
sorry, אתה שלמה ata Shlomo who all the secrets of the world
will be revealed to because שלמה got the wisdom right? So ישתה
יין וישתכר yishteh yayin veyishtaker. should drink wine and get drunk? So
I guess according to this maybe it's either prophesying it or it's
after he was king. I don't know. איכא
דאמרי ika de'amrei some say that I mean to say למואל מלך.
Lemuel melech. So maybe this is so right I was saying when
he was young before he was king but you're right maybe it's
reading it after he's already king she's trying to set him on
the straight and narrow. איכא דאמרי ika de'amrei some say מי שכל
רוזני עולם משכימים לפתחו mi shekol roznei olam mashkimim lepischo which is
the more simple sense of the רוזנים roznim all the one who
all the like the great princes of the world come up come
to your door and you have such a position of authority and
prestige ישתה יין yishteh yayin וישתכר. veyishtaker. Okay. אמר רבי יצחק Amar
Rabbi Yitzchak מנין שחזר שלמה והודה לאמו? minayin shechazar Shlomo v'hoda l'imo?
Where do you see in the end he admitted that his mother
was right that he shouldn't follow a life of drinking wine? דכתיב
dechativ כי בער אנכי מאיש. ki va'ar anochi me'ish. I am like
a animal of people. ולא בינת אדם לי v'lo binat adam li
I do not have the wisdom of men. כי בער אנכי מאיש
ki va'ar anochi me'ish מנח. miNoach. I am I am worse you
know דכתיב ויחל נח איש האדמה. vayachel Noach ish ha'adamah. ולא בינת
אדם לי v'lo binat adam li זה אדם הראשון. zeh Adam HaRishon.
I was you know I was I wasn't as smart as or
I was as stupid as נח Noach and as אדם הראשון Adam
HaRishon to follow wine. My mother is right and that's why he
left his life of drunkenness and became שלמה המלך. Shlomo HaMelech. Okay.
Let's try to just read a few more lines. אכל בחבורת מצוה
Achal b'chaburat mitzvah he ate in an in a mitzvah eating. אמר
רב אבהו Amar Rav Abbahu אינו חייב עד שיאכל בחבורה שכולה סריקין.
eino chayav ad sheyochal b'chabura shekulah serikin. You have to it's only
if you eat and at a gathering where everybody is worthless people.
Can't have any decent person there that would make the person not
a בן סורר ומורה if there's one decent person. והנן תנן V'hanan
tnan but didn't we say אכל בחבורת מצוה achal b'chaburat mitzvah אינו
נעשה בן סורר ומורה? eino na'aseh Ben Sorer u'Moreh? At a חבורת
מצוה chaburat mitzvah presumably at a חבורת מצוה chaburat mitzvah there are
decent people there.
Okay. טעמא דמצוה Ta'ama d'mitzvah and the only reason you're not a
בן סורר ומורה is not because of the company but because it's
a mitzvah gathering. הא לאו מצוה Ha lav mitzvah if it weren't
a mitzvah gathering even with the same company and presumably meaning some
decent people אע"ג דלאו כולה סריקין af al gav d'lav kulah serikin
even if they weren't all worthless
it sounds like you would be a בן סורר ומורה. So it
says no. הכא במאי עסקינן אע"ג דכולה סריקין. Hacha b'mai askinan af
al gav d'kulah serikin. No maybe you have a gathering for a
mitzvah that they're all worthless people. Okay but nevertheless כיון דבמצוה קא
עסיק keivan d'v'mitzvah ka asik even though the gathering is full of
a bunch of you know good-for-nothings since they're doing the mitzvah and
here's the explanation why לא מימשך. lo mimshach. Maybe you know you
only get drunk or whatever you know some people you know you
go to a wedding and you go straight to the bar and
you start drinking like a fish or whatever and you start stuffing
yourself at the smorg. But when it's not wedding it's not you
know when it's not those types of gatherings you wouldn't do it.
So therefore we're not afraid.
You mean it has to be a
non-mitzvah and they're all worthless. Okay let's just go one more line
get to the next two dots if you have to go go
but בעיבור החודש b'ibbur hachodesh but for a again similarly for a
gathering for the new month ומימרא דבשר ויין מסקי v'meimra d'basar v'yayin
maski it sounds like they drink wine eat meat and drink wine.
והתניא V'hatanya אין עולים לה אלא בפת דגן וקטנית בלבד. ein olim
lah ela b'pat dagan u'kitnit bilvad. The meal that they would have
to celebrate the new month would only be with like bread
and legumes. הכא במאי עסקינן אע"ג דאין עולים לה אלא פת וקטנית
ואיהו עסיק בבשר ויין ואכל. Hacha b'mai askinan af al gav d'ein
olim lah ela pat v'kitnit v'ihu asik b'basar v'yayin v'achal. Even though
everybody else is basically eating bread and he's there eating meat with
his own wine and meat and so you might say he's not
even part of the normal gathering he's just you know he's not
even eating what they're eating. No כיון דבמצוה קא עסיק keivan d'v'mitzvah
ka asik since they're doing a mitzvah לא מימשך. lo mimshach. It's
not a problem he won't be drawn after. תנו רבנן Tanu rabanan
אין עולים בעיבור החודש פחות מעשרה בני אדם. ein olim b'ibbur hachodesh
pachot m'asarah bnei adam. When they would gather to publicize the new
month it would be a gathering of at least ten people. ואין
עולים לה אלא בפת דגן וקטנית. v'ein olim lah ela b'pat dagan
u'kitnit. I don't know why this would be they would only have
certain bread. ואין עולים לה אלא לאור עיבורו v'ein olim lah ela
l'or iburo the night leading in like the night of ראש to
the
you know the 31st day of the
month which is the first of ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. ואין עולים
לה ביום אלא בלילה. v'ein olim lah bayom ela balailah. They wouldn't
they wouldn't do it at the day they would do it at
night like we just said they celebrated the night of ראש חודש.
Rosh Chodesh. והתניא V'hatanya didn't we teach אין עולים לה בלילה אלא
ביום? ein olim lah balailah ela bayom? They wouldn't do it at
night they'd do it in the day. כדאמר רבי חייא בר אבא
לבניי אחיפו ועולו אחיפו ופוקו. K'd'amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba l'vanai achifu
v'ulu achifu u'fuku. Like Rabbi Chiyya said to his son go get
early and go and get early and leave. כי היכי דלישמעו בכו
אינשי Ki heichi d'lishme'u b'chu inshi in order that people so listen
to you so I guess you should always come first and I
don't guess leave first but anyway. But the point still being that
when it says that they would do it at the day means
that they would like gather during the daytime but they would begin
the celebrations at night. Anyway so that was the gathering of ראש
חודש Rosh Chodesh and under those circumstances
he is not made a בן סורר ומורה. Okay.
We will continue tomorrow.